Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Company Offices Series, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated, bulk 1920-2000, (83 boxes plus oversize containers)
  - Agency in Force Office Subseries, 1850, 1920-1994 and undated
    - Blank form - application for life insurance, circa 1994
    - Industrial agent contract, undated
    - List of 1968-1969 memoranda contents, and memos, 1968 Jan.-1973 Nov., (4 folders)
    - Memos, 1968 Jan.-1969 July (Box 11)
    - Office Workers Union contract, 1952
    - Ordinary agent's contract (special), undated
    - Regular ordinary agent's contract, undated
    - North Carolina Mutual Life [Raleigh] policy, 1850 with letter attached, 1969 (Box OV2)
      Mailed to NC Mutual's offices in 1969 by an executive in Baltimore, this life insurance policy was sold by an insurance organization in Raleigh by the same name, which organized in the 1840s and disbanded in the 1860s. A blank life insurance policy on a slave printed by this same company also exists in the Charles Hunter Papers in the Rubenstein Library at Duke.
    - Life insurance policies, 1921-1926, (3 folders) (Box OV3)
    - Matted life insurance policy, 1941
      [Some of the materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as contents should be photocopied before being handled.]
    - Policies, 1921-1926, (3 folders) (Box OV4)
    - Laminated policies, 1913, 1919, 1935
    - One million and a quarter drive chart, mortgages to go to Century Life, 1919, 1927
    - Training records and reports, 1962-1963 (Box OV5)
    - Ledger, 1967-1986 (Box OV6)
    - General ledger, 1982 Apr.-1984 Dec. (Box OV7)
    - A Birds-eye View of the Manager's Job, undated (Box OV8)
    - Blank policy, circa 1952
  - Auditing Office Subseries, 1904-1905, 1922-1950, 1972-1987 and undated, bulk 1970s-1980s
    Includes files relating to audits of NCM and its district offices, as well as material from the NCM Audit Committee. Audits were conducted by outside firms such as Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells and Ernst and Ernst.
    - Accountants and other correspondence, 1980 (Box 11)
    - Accounting audits, NCM, 1983-1987
    - BC Audit Committee, 1980, (2 folders)
    - Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells:
      - Financial statement reports, 1981-1983
      - NCM reports, 1981-1982
      - Reports for NCM, 1981-1985, (2 folders)
    - Ernst and Ernst: CPA review of NCM, 1972-1973
    - Internal auditors home office audits, 1980
    - NCM Audit committee: (Box 12)
      - Agendas, 1978-1979
      - Meetings, 1977-1985, (10 folders)
      - Miscellaneous documents, 1979-1981
    - NCM internal audits, 1974-1984, (2 folders)
    - PA audit, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Regular audits, 1980
    - Financial statements and data, 1904-1905, 1922-1944 (Box OV4)
    - Financial statements, underwriters' pocket charts, death claims paid, 1922-1950
    - Financial statements, ordinary mortality experience statements, NIA questionnaire, 1927-1941
    - Ernst and Ernst checklist, undated (Box OV9)
  - Controller Subseries, 1945-2001 and undated
    The Office of the Controller is in charge of coordinating, planning, and reporting on financial activities, including bookkeeping, accounting, and financial reporting. The material in this subseries consists of the Report of the Controller to the Board of Directors for NCM, ranging from 1986-2001. Also contains annual reports, annual statements, and Bonds and Stocks Owned statements.
    - Controller position, staffing, duties, 1960s (Box 13)
    - NCM federal income tax return, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Report of the Controller, 1986-2001, (7 folders) (Box 13)
    - Abstracts from the Tenth Annual Statement, 1908 (Box 14)
    - Annual reports, 1963, 1987-2003, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Annual statements, 1945-1967, 1978-1988, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Bonds and stocks owned, 1945-1978, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Ratings and rankings from Best's and National Underwriter, 1964-1986 (Box 14)
    - Report of the Controller, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Annual statement, 1960 (Box OV4)
  - Corporate Planning Subseries, 1947-1952, 1958-1981 and undated, (9 boxes)
    Contains detailed materials on the research, planning, execution, and progress of the construction of the new Mutual Plaza home office, including blueprints for the home office and the Chatham annex. Also includes plans for organizational and management restructuring, business plans by company department, reports, manuals for the functions and duties of home office organization, reviews of data processing, and correspondence with management consulting firms and other companies. Additionally contains alphabetized files regarding general correspondence, solicitation, and donation requests. Includes information regarding Murray Marvin (one of the directors of Corporate Planning) during his time at both Jackson Mutual and NC Mutual. Note: The structure of the Corporate Planning department changed several times over the course of NC Mutual's history. Corporate Planning and Public Relations merged under Murray Marvin in 1967 and was reorganized into Planning and Communications around 1976.
    - Corporate Planning files (Box 15-24)
    - Floor plans, undated, (2 folders) (Box OV2)
    - Clipping, 1966
    - Monthly review of office construction and costs, 1965 (Box OV8)
    - Clippings, 1970
    - Display panel and blueprints, 1952-1958 (Box OV10)
    - Blueprint, Mutual Plaza (?), circa 1960s
    - Very large blueprints, 24x36", (5 items) (Opaperfolder 4)
  - Executive Committee Subseries, 1922-2003 and undated, bulk from 1972-1989 [RESTRICTED]
    Mainly pertains to business conducted by the Executive Committee, a standing committee of the Board of Directors, which is made up of a minimum of five Directors, at least one of which is required to be an outside Director. Material from the Salary Committee, another standing committee of the Board, is also included in this subseries. The Salary Committee consists of five of the Directors, one of whom must be the President of the company.
    [Subseries is restricted for 25 years from date of last created folder, or 2028; until that date, written permission must be given by donor before contents can be accessed.]
    - Beechwood Cemetery, 1939-1966, 1998-2003, and undated (Box 25)
    - Housing project for home office employees, 1948
    - Minutes of Budget Control Committee, 1928-1944
    - Mrs. W.D. Hill, 1945
    - Bessie Whitted mortgage, 1952
    - D.C. Deans, Richmond City Council, 1952
    - Board of Directors, 1927-1952
    - Gaillard correspondence, 1970
    - Committees, 1941-1972
    - Great Lakes region, 1972-1975
    - Good Citizen Life Insurance Company, 1973
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1922-1938 and undated
    - Response to Business Week's Upheaval in Life Insurance, 1984
    - Minute book of Budget Control Committee, 1928-1944
    - Salary Committee:
      - Hay Associates, 1978-1986
      - Hay Associates compensation study, 1985
      - Clerical salary adjustments, 1972-1984
      - Nominating Committee, 1987-1988
      - Merit increases and promotion recommendations, 1987-1988
      - Agency regional bonuses, 1976-1990
      - Board meeting, 1983
      - Data processing job descriptions, 1979-1989 and undated
      - Performance standards worksheets, 1973-1975
      - Annual Statement Committee, 1979-1981
      - Employee retirement dates, 1975-1981
      - Net annualized premiums, 1975-1976
      - Notes, charts and memoranda, 1978-1991 and undated
      - Salary information, 1979
      - Salary charts, 1980-1983
      - Clerical salary adjustments, 1973-1988
      - Salary increases, senior officers and directors, (J. W. Goodloe on cover), 1977
    - Salary Committee: (Box 26)
      - Charity fund committee, 1931-1932
      - John C. Blackman claim, 1972
      - Salary Study, 1956
      - Memoranda, charts, guides, and notes, 1988-1989
      - Notes, memoranda, and charts, 1986-1988 and undated
      - Agendas and memoranda, 1989-1990 and undated
      - Officer and administrative salaries, 1969-1985 and undated
      - Charts and memoranda, 1987-1988
      - Proposed budget, 1987
      - Salary forms, undated
      - Salary breakdown by department, 1977-1986
      - News clippings, 1985
      - Annual statement and proposed budget, 1985-1986
      - Home office salary schedules, 1924-1964
      - Salary memos, 1926-1958
      - Salary adjustment notes and charts, 1989
      - Salaries, 1978-1981, 1987, (2 folders)
      - Salary charts, 1976-1981
      - Salary adjustments, 1969-1989
      - Salary increases, early retirements, position cuts, 1989-1990
      - Salary increases, etc, 1981-1988
    - Salary Committee: (Box 27)
      - Salary increases, etc, 1981-1988, (2 folders)
      - Salaries, 1960s-1970s
      - Salary increases, 1980-1982, (2 folders)
    - Officers' salaries, 1946-1964 (Box OV1)
    - Officers' salaries and operations analysis, 1974, 1989
    - Drives letter, 1922 Feb. 1 (Box OV8)
    - Envelope with notes and directions, undated
    - Good Citizens Life Insurance Co. agent report, 1973
    - Financial statements of other companies, income and investment table, 1952-1955
    - Salary expenses and increases by district, 1980-1985
    - Salary worksheets, reports, and bonus projections, 1977-1980
    - Assets and stocks of life insurance companies, salary study, 1969 (Box OV10)
  - Facilities Subseries, 1950-1966, 1990-1998 and undated
    Contains material concerning the home office at Mutual Plaza. It includes photos of the construction and dedication of Mutual Plaza, as well as blueprints, manuals, guides, and reservation forms. It also includes a Department of Housing and Urban Development (DHUD) award for building design. Arranged in original order as received.
    - The Whetstone, Mutual Plaza issues, 1963-1964 (Box 28)
    - New home office - programs, promotional material, and invitation, 1963-1966
    - Moving to Mutual Plaza manual, 1966
    - Construction of Mutual Plaza photos, 1963-1964 and undated, (12 folders)
    - Dedication - Mutual Plaza, 1950-1966 and undated, (3 folders)
    - HVAC evaluation, 1990
    - NCM building layout, undated
    - Stressteel post-tensioning publication, after 1966
    - Facility reservations and related forms, 1994-1998, (4 folders) (Box 29)
    - Department of Housing and Urban Development: Honor Awards for Design Excellence, 1966
    - Clippings, 1966 (Box OV1)
    - Floor plans and blue prints, 1963-1964 (Box OV10)
  - Medical Department Subseries, 1922, 1955, 1978, 1984-1990, 2002, bulk 1980s-1990s
    Materials include a history of the department, which was established by Dr. A.T. Moore in 1916 and disbanded after 2002, as well as print material produced for health campaigns, and biographical information on directors Dr. Charles D. Watts and Dr. John T. Daniel. Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title. Other archival records and memorabilia on medical topics and health campaigns can be found in the Printed Material, Publicity, and Memorabilia Series.
    - Curriculum Vitae, Dr. Watts and miscellaneous Medical Department material, 1955, 1978, 1984-1986 (Box 29)
    - Daniel, John T., M.D., Senior Vice President position description, 1987
    - Employee Wellness Program, 2002
    - Medical Bulletin: Tuberculosis, 1922 Feb. 3, from Director Dr. Donnell, two pages
    - Medical Staff's Agency Ordinary Series Product and User's Manual binder, 1993-1999
    - NCM History of the Medical Department: 1916-1988, circa 1988
    - Raising Healthy Children, Dr. Alvin Poussaint, 1990, talk, includes photo of his visit to Durham
    - Swat That Fly, circa 1920s, health campaign circular from Director, illustrated (ink)
    - Sign, undated (Box OV8)
  - Office of the President Subseries, 1903-2002 and undated, bulk from 1950s-1990s [RESTRICTED]
    This subseries consists of material from the offices and files of five of NCM's nine presidents: William J. Kennedy, Jr., Asa T. Spaulding, Sr., Joseph W. Goodloe, William J. Kennedy, III, and Bert Collins. The contents relate mainly to the periods during which these presidents held the office, though in some cases there is material from previous positions they held within NCM and apart from the company. Much of the material includes files relating to the execution of company business, correspondence, and personnel matters. The majority of the material in the subseries originates from the offices of Kennedy, III and Collins.
    [Files in the Office of the President Subseries are restricted for 25 years from the last year of each presidency. Permission to access these records must be granted by NC Mutual in writing prior to use. Otherwise, contents are open to research. Personnel files found in this series have been separated and are closed for 75 years from the date of creation of material, or 2074.]
    - William J. Kennedy, Jr., (5 boxes)
      Served as President of NC Mutual from 1952-1958. Much of the contents of this subseries comprises the materials that Kennedy, Jr. used to document the history of North Carolina Mutual, as well as the wide variety of historical sketches he produced. Other material in this subseries relates to general company business from his tenure at NCM both as the Corporate Secretary and as President, including a letter of support for Pauli Murray's admission to the New York State Bar Association in 1948. Additionally, there is material relating to his tenure as the President of the Bankers Fire and Casualty Insurance Company.
      [Some of the material found in box 33 is fragile and should be handled with care. Contact reference archivist before using, as material may need photocopying before use.]
      - Bankers Fire and Casualty Insurance Company
        - Bankers Fire and Casualty: (Box 30)
          - 1929, 1962-1968, and undated, (2 folders)
          - By-laws, WJK resignation, and miscellaneous documents, 1960-1968
          - Christmas message, 1963-1967
          - Correspondence and miscellaneous business, 1954, 1958-1965, 1967, and undated, (2 folders)
          - Executive Committee, 1963-1968
          - Expansion program, 1956-1962
          - Minutes, Executive Committee, and Board, 1964-1968
          - Statements of Condition, 1960-1968
        - Bankers Fire and Casualty: (Box 32)
          - 1965-1968 and undated
          - 1921, 1926, 1963-1968
          - Personnel File, 1965-1967
      - NCM Company Business
        - Century Life Insurance Company, 1927 and undated (Box 30)
        - Golden Anniversary program, 1949
        - Letter of recommendation for Pauli Murray to the N.Y. Bar from W. J. Kennedy, Jr., 1948
        - Letter regarding unemployment from Alabama Department of Industrial Relations, 1946 June 1
        - Liberia Today, 1956
        - Minutes from meetings of the Actuarial staff, 1957-1959
        - Miscellaneous documents, 1965 and undated
        - Miscellaneous NCM business, 1924, 1927, 1933, 1944-1955, 1959-1961, 1964-1966, and undated, (2 folders)
        - Mortgage loans, 1944, 1950-1956, and undated
        - National Association of Insurance Commissioners, 1949-1953 (Box 31)
        - NCM Real Estate, 1931-1953
        - NIA Convention, 1966
        - North Carolina state insurance laws, 1949-1950
        - Other insurers' policies, 1957 and undated
        - Requests for deferment to the Selective Service Draft Board, 1942-1944
        - Speeches, 1950, 1953-1965
        - Afro-American insurance companies, 1927-1930 and undated (Box 32)
        - Annual reports of banking institutions owned and operated by Negroes, 1944-1960
        - Board of Directors meetings binder, 1925, 1950-1964
        - Correspondence between Abner Lee and "Lee," 1965 Apr. and undated
        - Durham Herald clipping regarding 15th annual National Negro Insurance Association (NIA) convention, 1935 May 22
        - Financial statements, banks, and savings and loan associations, Durham, 1955
        - Forms committee, 1946, 1949-1953, and undated
        - Mortgage loans, 1952, 1957-1959, and undated
        - Miscellaneous historical papers, 1942, 1947, circa 1959
        - NCM annual statements folder, 1909-1910, 1914-1915, 1918-1955, 1957-1965
        - Officers' salaries from various insurance companies, 1955-1956
        - Population statistics, 1943-1965 and undated
        - Records of insurance companies owned by Negroes, 1943-1958
        - Sales drives - Agents' conferences, 1919, 1923, and undated
      - NCM History Project
        - A Brief Outline History of the Organization, Growth, and Development of the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1898-1931 by Asa T. Spaulding (Box 31)
        - A Symbol of Progress: 1898-1966, History of the NC Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1966, (5 folders)
        - Biographical sketches of E.R. Merrick and Aaron McDuffie Moore, circa 1967 and undated
        - Correspondence with N.J. Board of Education, 1954, 1963
        - Dr. J.H. Taylor, consultant - history and correspondence, 1960-1967
        - History of J.M. Avery and other NCM history and business info, 1914, 1931, 1942-1945, and undated
        - NCM Historical Sketches and Supplements, 1930, 1935, 1939, 1944-1945, 1955, 1961, and undated (Box 32)
        - The North Carolina Mutual Story - A Symbol of Progress: 1899-1966(the founding of NC Mutual), handwritten manuscript, 1966, (9 folders) (Box 33)
        - History of NC Mutual: (Box 34)
          - Biography of founders and other material for writing NCM history, 1959
          - Miscellaneous reproduced photos and other material, 1904, 1943-1959, and undated, (2 folders)
        - John Merrick biographical notes, 1932-1943 and undated
        - Miscellaneous photos and documents for the NC Mutual history project, 1903, 1908-1910, 1928, 1937, 1948, 1963-1965, and undated
        - Miscellaneous photos and loose materials, 1912, circa 1950, and undated
        - Miss S.E. Bailey, consultant - NC Mutual history, 1960
        - Mr. W.J. Kennedy, Jr. to Mr. John A. Spaulding, 1960-1963, 1966
        - Mrs. G.P. Lipscomb - NC Mutual history project, 1966
        - NCM history and historical sketches, circa 1934, 1944, 1959, and undated
        - NCM History Committee:
          - 1962-1970
          - Illustration labels, 1969 and undated
          - Memos to directors, 1959-1969
          - "History of other Life Companies" correspondence file, 1959-1967
        - University Press - UNC-Chapel Hill - Mr. W.J. Kennedy, Jr., 1963-1965
    - Asa T. Spaulding
      Spaulding served as President of NCM from 1959-1967. Mainly includes speeches and press releases, as well as some material relating to company business. Much more information can be found in the Asa T. and Elna Spaulding Papers held in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
      - A. T. Spaulding biographical sketches, 1933, 1937, 1956, 1961, 1968, and undated (Box 32)
      - Newspaper clippings, circa 1959
      - Press release, circa 1957
      - 7th annual G.W. Cox Sales for NCM 60th anniversary, 1959 (Box 35)
      - 50th and 60th anniversaries, 1949, 1959-1960
      - 60th anniversary and miscellaneous newspapers, 1954-1961 and undated
      - A Christmas Wish by A.T. Spaulding, undated
      - A Message by A.T. Spaulding, 1934
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1963 and undated
      - Histories of Negro Insurance, 1943 and undated
      - Membership certificate from National Defense Executive Reserve, 1959 July 1
      - NCM publications, 1947, 1966
      - N.L. Gregg retirement, 1966
      - Northern Frontier Planning Committee - Appreciation Production to President Asa T. Spaulding, 1959
      - Partners in Business by A.T. Spaulding, 1940
      - Pay stabilization, 1951 and undated
      - Progress report, 1963
      - Releases and speeches, 1943, 1956, 1961-1963, 1968-1969
      - Report to the Policyholders, 1961-1968, (3 folders)
      - Special Reports on Major Business Problems from Business Week, 1965
      - Speeches, 1932, 1938, 1956, 1964-1967, (2 folders)
      - The Presidents' Council of the American Institute of Management, 1965
      - Youth opportunity campaign, 1965
    - Joseph W. Goodloe
      Goodloe served as President from 1968-1972. Contains some material from his time as Corporate Secretary. There are very few materials present within the collection from Goodloe's tenure at NCM.
      - Philadelphia office 30th anniversary, 1968 (Box 32)
      - Dedication Committee for new home office - Mutual Plaza, 1965-1966, (2 folders)
      - Letter concerning employment contracts for former Unity Mutual Life Insurance Company officials, 1971 (Box 35)
      - Report to policyholders, 1971-1972, (2 folders)
    - William J. Kennedy, III, (7 boxes)
      Kennedy, III, son of William Kennedy Jr., served as President of NC Mutual from 1972-1990. Material relates to general company business, external and internal correspondence, mergers with and reinsurance of other insurance companies, and information pertaining to other organizations with which NC Mutual was affiliated (the contents are categorized as: company business/personnel, correspondence, other insurance companies, and other organizations).
      [Some personnel records were removed to Personnel Subseries and are closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
      - Company Business/Personnel
        Contains material relating to both financial and non-financial aspects of the company business, including but not limited to matters relating to personnel. Material is organized alphabetically by the size of the material. There is also one personal letter from his parents, 1958.
        - Accountants' Opinion report, 1981 Dec. 31 (Box 36)
        - Asa T. Spaulding Insurance Hall of Fame, 1984-1985
        - Banquet tributes, 1978 and undated
        - Blank retirement Certificate of Service, undated
        - Blue Cross Blue Shield stock purchase, 1986 Nov.-1987 Jan.
        - Board of Directors fees and committees of the Board, 1985 Mar.
        - Board items, 1973-1984, 1989 and undated
        - Construction offers, 1988
        - Cost Committee: Life Office Management Association, 1954-1963, (3 folders)
        - Employee and committee info for NCM Board of Directors, 1970, 1973, 1984-1987
        - Harvard Business Review, 1973
        - Historic documents: Centennial of Durham's Stanford-Warren library, 1990; obituaries for William Kennedy Jr., 1985, and N. H. Beale, 1990
        - Historical Experience of the Reinsured Group Business, 1976
        - Historical Sketch by W.J. Kennedy, Jr., three versions circa 1934, 1949, 1957
        - Introduction to Life/70, Student Guide, circa 1978, (2 folders)
        - Introduction to Life/70, Textbook, circa 1978 (Box 37)
        - Martin Luther King Jr. memorial program, 1985
        - Merrick-Moore scholarship advertising, press releases, clippings, 1935-1936
          [The contents of this folder are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as material should be photocopied before handling.]
        - Md. Insurance Division hearing in petition for approval of contract and reinsurance of Mutual Benefit Society of Baltimore, 1977
        - Miscellaneous company business, circa 1970s
        - New South Life Insurance Company financial statements and information, 1973-1975
        - North American Insurance Company contracts, 1980
        - NCM book review
        - NCM building, Vierendeel trusses, 1977-1980
        - NCM employee evaluation plan, 1961-1962
        - NCM Employment handbook, guidelines, and company information, undated
        - NCM Group Reinsurance Program report, 1982 July 28